<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root> [Letter from Marian Baldwin, June 30, 1917]
    <!--La Touraine is an ocean liner that traveled from France to New York in the late 1890s and early 1900s-->
    On Board La Touraine, June 30th, 1917. <scenicdescription>Even now that we are out of sight of
        land,</scenicdescription> it seems impossible that I am actually off to France and, for the
    first time in my life, traveling alone. Everything has happened so quickly since the
        <organization>American Fund for French Wounded</organization> found an opening for me in
        <city>Paris</city> that I suppose I am still somewhat <emotions> dazed and
        bewildered.</emotions> The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and that I can't
    look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I have had a bit of a
    taste in New York of the work that the <organization>A. F. F. W.</organization> is doing but its
    Headquarters in <city>Paris</city> will be different in some ways I <slang>fancy.</slang> I
    can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few girls of my age are
    getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you encourage me on my great
    adventure and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of late. <scenicdescription>As
        we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with two absurd tugs puffing
        alongside,</scenicdescription> I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought
    was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line again! <shipdescription>It was very
    quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky and one star after
    another appeared.</shipdescription> I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in Lakewood and that
    your thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that moment. Somehow distance
    does not separate, after all. We waited near the <landmark>Statue of Liberty</landmark> until
    midnight—a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on board. This individual was
        <metaphor>shrouded in mystery</metaphor> until we put to sea when it was given out that the
    party which had clambered aboard in the night was none other than the Italian Mission.
    <!--    The Italian Mission was a group that traveled from Italy to New York in the late 1910s.-->
    Our spirits rose at once for, what with Frank Sayre on the boat and these distinguished Italian
    gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe.
        <scenicdescription>However, thus far we have but two destroyers following
        us.</scenicdescription>
    <shipdescrption>They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side, and
        seem to be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in this war.</shipdescrption>
    <!--"this war"=world war one"-->
    A sailor informed me this morning that we
    weren't in much danger for the first four or five days but that after that I might see some
    excitement. Here's hoping! <shipdescription>I have a small inside cabin</shipdescription> and my
    room-mate is quite a character.
    <!--  Haiti was allied with France during world war one      -->
    <characterdescription> She is a native of Haiti,voluble and very portly—has four large pieces of
        baggage in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a Mother Hubbard and smokes
        countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense!</characterdescription> When I appeared,
    there didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, <characterdescription>luckily I am
        small,</characterdescription> and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings!
    She really isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she didn't think we would
    fight and from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son <characterdescription>who has been
    fighting with the French since the beginning of the war but will never go back to the Front now,
    having lost some fingers off each hand. </characterdescription>She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more
    than his fingers. </root>
