<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root> [Letter from Marian Baldwin, June 30, 1917] <!--La Touraine is an ocean liner that traveled from France to New York in the late 1890s and early 1900s-->
    <letter1>On Board La Touraine, June 30th, 1917. <scenicdescription>Even now that we are out of
            sight of land,</scenicdescription> it seems impossible that I am actually off to France
        and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone. Everything has happened so quickly
        since the <organization>American Fund for French Wounded</organization> found an opening for
        me in <city>Paris</city> that I suppose I am still somewhat <emotions> dazed and
            bewildered.</emotions> The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and that I
        can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I have had a
        bit of a taste in New York of the work that the <organization>A. F. F. W.</organization> is
        doing but its Headquarters in <city>Paris</city> will be different in some ways I
            <slang>fancy.</slang> I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize
        how few girls of my age are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made
        you encourage me on my great adventure and send me along a path which has proved so
        dangerous of late. <scenicdescription>As we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with
            two absurd tugs puffing alongside,</scenicdescription> I know that many eyes were moist
        and that the same thought was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company will see
        that sky-line again! <shipdescription>It was very quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by
            little, the glow faded from the sky and one star after another
            appeared.</shipdescription> I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in
        Lakewood and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that
        moment. Somehow distance does not separate, after all. We waited near the <landmark>Statue
            of Liberty</landmark> until midnight—a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on
        board. This individual was <metaphor>shrouded in mystery</metaphor> until we put to sea when
        it was given out that the party which had clambered aboard in the night was none other than
        the Italian Mission.
        <!--    The Italian Mission was a group that traveled from Italy to New York in the late 1910s.-->
        Our spirits rose at once for, what with Frank Sayre on the boat and these distinguished
        Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe.
            <scenicdescription>However, thus far we have but two destroyers following
            us.</scenicdescription>
        <shipdescrption>They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side,
            and seem to be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in this
            war.</shipdescrption>
        <!--"this war"=world war one"--> A sailor informed me this morning that we weren't in much
        danger for the first four or five days but that after that I might see some excitement.
        Here's hoping! <shipdescription>I have a small inside cabin</shipdescription> and my
        room-mate is quite a character. <!--  Haiti was allied with France during world war one      -->
        <characterdescription> She is a native of Haiti,voluble and very portly—has four large
            pieces of baggage in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a Mother
            Hubbard and smokes countless thin cigarettes that smell like
            incense!</characterdescription> When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room for
        me but, as she says, <characterdescription>luckily I am small,</characterdescription> and I
        was soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings! She really isn't bad and after
        looking me over carefully told me that she didn't think we would fight and from that time
        has beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son <characterdescription>who has been
            fighting with the French since the beginning of the war but will never go back to the
            Front now, having lost some fingers off each hand. </characterdescription>She is so
        thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his fingers.</letter1>
    <letter2><date early-July="Summer"/>July 8th, 1917. Friday night we entered the war zone at
            <time evening="late">seven o'clock</time> but you would never know it. Aside from
        boat-drills and sleeping on deck people act as usual. The officers on the boat are very
        particular about the drills; several times the alarm has sounded and we have been taught
        just what to do in case we are hit. It's very funny to see <visualdescription
            people="practicing drilling ">the people rush below for their valuables, strapping on
            their life preservers as they go (which we always have near at hand wherever we are -on
            deck or in the saloon). In about <timemeasurement minutes="short">five
                minutes</timemeasurement> we are lined up, divided into groups in front of our own
            particular life-boats which have been swung out over the sea ready to lower. Every one
            is checked off and each man is told what woman he is to save. (Great excitement at this
            point as no one of the men wants to save the lady detailed to him, but some one in
            another boat!) We all stand about looking too absurd and bumping into each other's life
            preservers on the crowded upper deck. Finally the signal is given which releases us, and
            we all file down again to take off the clumsy heavy jackets of safety and regale
            ourselves with various amusements on the deck.</visualdescription> Rumor has it that two
        ships have been sunk, one in the course ahead of where we were yesterday and the other about
        an hour behind us. No one knows how many lives were lost. Perhaps those three submarines
        were more fact than fiction after all. It is thought that we should make Bordeaux by Tuesday
        morning if all goes well and that the convoy which should have met us days ago will be with
        us to-night. This being <timemeasurement day="Sunday">Sunday,</timemeasurement><visualdescription men="well-dressed">  the boys on
        board are very much dressed up, that is to say they are wearing clean shirts and have their
        hair brushed!</visualdescription> It's a perfect day, warm and cloudless, and I've been lying in the sun adding
        to my coat of tan. We all feel quite sad that the voyage is so nearly over -it has been such
        loads of fun and I shall hate saying good-by to every one. La Touraine </letter2>
    <letter3>Baccarat, <date lateJuly="Summer">July 24th, 1918.</date> <weatherdescripton warm ="La Touraine">>A wonderful moon to-night and the countryside transformed
        under its silvery radiance. We have had terrible nights for a week now and we are all more
        or less worn out with little sleep and long hot days.</weatherdescripton><warcommentary planes ="European"> The German planes have been coming
        over as regularly as clock work and as this sector is unimportant compared to others farther
        up the line, we aren't really protected at all. An English aëroplane field lies some miles
        in the country behind us and they do what they can to help drive off the enemy planes but
        they aren't able to accomplish much as they have a huge area to cover and very little
        equipment. I thought I knew what an air raid was like after being in Paris for six months,
        but in comparison, those raids seem like mere child's play. Ever since the moon was two days
        old, the Germans haven't missed a single night and as soon as it gets dark, we hear the
        ominous whirr. At once the peace and quiet evaporate as if by magic and the whole atmosphere
        becomes alive with expectation and silent fears. The church bell is set ringing furiously
        and the doleful sirens begin their wailing from several parts of the town at once. Windows
        are thrown open and people begin to call back and forth to each other. This lasts only a few
        moments and then complete and utter silence. Every one has gone below ground and the town
        lies waiting in the moonlight. At first I refused to take refuge "dans la cave" (the cellar)
        partly because I didn't want to be smothered to death beneath the plaster and brick walls of
        the house. A direct hit seemed infinitely preferable to that, also, strange as it may seem,
        I had no desire to get out of bed. I had lost so much sleep and had been working so hard,
        that night generally found me thankful for a bed. Even if the noise of guns kept me awake I
        could rest, and the moist, chilly cellar held no charms! However, I found that staying "au
        lit" in the midst of an air raid was unheard of in these parts and <characterinteraction othercivilians="frightened"> Madame M. rushed into my
        room and with tears in her eyes implored me to accompany her below. The poor little old lady
        fears the avions above all else and the sound of their motors drives her into a frenzy of
        fear. In order to calm her I threw on a few clothes and we stumbled down the narrow stairs
        and spent the dark hours huddled in a little group around a candle that sputtered and
        flickered in the draughty, damp air. Our party consists always of Madame, Joséphine, a
        French officer, who is likewise billeted in the house, and myself. The first night that we
        spent in the cellar, he was already below when we ladies arrived. I have never seen a more
        droll figure and I wonder now how I ever kept my face straight. He was attired in pink and
        white pajamas and on his head at a jaunty angle sat his most dressy uniform cap covered with
        gold braid and pale blue broadcloth! Undoubtedly he felt it added dignity and a certain
        modesty to his appearance. As we came down he was pacing up and down the mud floor in his
        bare feet! He told me that he had been through four years of war, had seen comrades blown to
        atoms right beside him. "I know what these bombs can do, I have seen with my two eyes, it is
        folly not to seek shelter in a raid, so when I hear the Boches coming, I leap from my bed et
        je me sauve, Mademoiselle." I felt that he was right and that the French must be thinking
        some of us very children who are still taking war as a game, and looking upon our folly and
        daring as bravery. Surely no one has any business to waste his life. For the first and
        perhaps the last time our lives are infinitely important and useful. This officer is really
        a very good sort and entertains us during the long hours with tales of all sorts. We discuss
        the war at great length and try and keep our minds occupied and off of the terrible sounds
        overhead.</characterinteraction> It's great for my French and I am improving. Sometimes the noise is deafening, the
        anti-air-craft guns keep up a continuous fire and yet the Germans don't seem to be the least
        bit daunted and fly just above the tops of the trees, placing their bombs with the most
        pitiless accuracy. <waraction casuality ="Civilians">Last night three houses in this neighborhood were hit and in the old
            mill, half a block away, a young woman and her little girl were killed.</waraction> It was a ghastly few
        hours. <warreaction fearful ="Madame M.">Madame had one fit of hysterics right after another and threw herself about the
        cellar in a spasm of fear, trembling violently and moaning and crying. It was one of the
        most pathetic and terrible sights I have ever seen. We tried to quiet her but as the bombs
        were literally falling all about us, there wasn't much one could say to cheer her.</warreaction><waraction planes ="raid"> When one
        plane had dropped its supply of horror it would dash back and in ten minutes another would
        be swooping and sailing above us and the crash and uproar would begin again. In order that
        they may see better to do their hideous work, they drop a flare which illuminates the town
        as though it were day. By the time the strong light has burned itself out several bombs can
        be neatly placed. The raid generally begins about nine o'clock and the planes come over in
        rapid succession until dawn. </waraction>It is extraordinary what an effect the sound of the German
        motor has upon one. The noise even at a great distance will wake me out of a sound sleep
        whereas our own planes can fly right past my window and I never know it. This morning the
        town is really upset. Last night's raid was the worst yet.<waraction casulity="French"> Two of our soldiers in the
        Evacuation Hospital were killed and a great number of French. A bomb lit across the street
        from the Y and this morning I found all my canteen windows smashed into a thousand pieces.
        The Boches dropped several notes all over the streets written in French which said "If you
        think last night's raid a bad one, wait for to-night. We will break all records."</waraction> The
        consequence is that the morale is not very good, every one worn out with no sleep, horror
        piled on horror, and the anticipation of worse things to-night. 
        Later -Same day. To-day is a
        sizzler, quite the worse we've had. The dust pours in at the windows and the canteen is
        black with flies. We've been making lemonade for hundreds of hot, tired soldiers. They come
        in white with dust and the perspiration running down their cheeks.<characterdescription soldiers ="hot"> No cotton uniforms to be
        issued this summer; the boys have to wear their woolly winter ones, poor darlings, and can't
        even take their blouses off. The result is that if this weather continues the entire A. E.
        F. will be reduced to a grease spot! We have made a hundred and sixty liters of lemonade
        to-day; the canteen has been jammed to the doors since early morning with men, tongues
        hanging out and clammering for something "cold and wet."</characterdescription> The boys stand around in a huge
        ring while we make the lemonade, offering all kinds of advice and suggestions; I have quite
        a time keeping them on the other side of the counter; they all want to help but we can't use
        more than three stalwart and professional lemon squeezers! When the huge tank is finally
        filled, there are loud cheers from all present and it is worth anything to see the gusto
        with which they dispatch the lemonade down their dusty throats. How I love this place, -it's
        perfectly great being attached to a division. Westy, Alice, Squibby, who have canteens in
        little villages nearby, are in here quite frequently and we compare notes and discuss
        methods, and our various problems at length. I imagine some of us will shortly be sent back
        to Aix as our month of change is nearing its end. I can't tell you how I hate the thought of
        leaving, although of course I want to be where I am most needed. The simplicity of this
        place is a great contrast to Aix and does appeal to me so much more than the gay whirl down
        there with the Casino and all its marble halls and broad terraces. There the boys come and
        go and you do all you can to cheer them, but here they aren't on leave and are up against
        the real thing, and, if possible, need a bit of feminine companionship more than anywhere
        else. Also one belongs to a unit and after a while you come to feel a very distinct sense of
        proprietorship, your hopes and fears and special prayers are centered about the men of your
        outfit and their failures and successes are very much your own. O! I do hope that the Y will
        let me stay right where I am. I have made up my mind of course to be a good soldier whatever
        comes, but I am hoping, hoping hard every minute that I shall be allowed to stay.</warcommentary>
    </letter3></root>
