<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <title>Leaves</title>
    <authorsname>Lloyd Schwartz</authorsname>
    <p>Every October it becomes important, no, necessary to see the leaves turning, to be surrounded
        by leaves turning; it's not just the symbolism, to confront in the death of the year your
        death, <imagery>one blazing farewell appearance,</imagery> though the irony isn't lost on
        you that nature is most seductive when it's about to die, <imagery>flaunting the dazzle of
            its incipient exit,</imagery> an ending that at least so far the effects of human
        progress (pollution, acid rain) have not yet frightened you enough to make you believe is
        real; that is, you know this ending is a deception because of course nature is always
        renewing itself— the trees don't die, they just pretend, go out in style, and return in
        style: a new style.</p>
    <!--    Lines 10-12 are a commentary on the fact that nothing  dies but is instead "reborn" into something new-->
    <p> Is it deliberate how far they make you go especially if you live in the city to get far
        enough away from home to see not just<scenicdescription visual="nature"> trees but only
            trees? The boring highways, roadsigns, high speeds, 10-axle trucks passing you as if
            they were in an even greater hurry than you to look at leaves: so you drive in terror
            for literal hours and it looks like <weather>rain, or snow,</weather> but it's probably
            just clouds (too cloudy to see any color?)</scenicdescription> and you wonder, given the
        poverty of your memory, which road had the most color last year, but it doesn't matter since
        you're probably too late anyway, or too early— whichever road you take will be the wrong one
        and you've probably come all this way for nothing.</p>
    <p><scenicdescription>You'll be driving along depressed when suddenly a cloud will move and the
            sun will muscle through and ignite the hills.</scenicdescription> It may not last.
        Probably won't last. But for a moment the whole world comes to. Wakes up. Proves it lives.
        It lives— <colors>red, yellow, orange, brown, russet, ocher, vermilion, gold.</colors> <imagery>Flame
        and rust. Flame and rust, the permutations of burning. You're on fire. Your eyes are on
        fire. It won't last, you don't want it to last. You can't stand any more. But you don't want
        it to stop. It's what you've come for. It's what you'll come back for. It won't stay with
        you, but you'll remember that it felt like nothing else you've felt or something you've felt
        that also didn't last.</imagery></p>
    <metadata> Copyright © 1992 by Lloyd Schwartz. From Goodnight, Gracie (The University of Chicago
        Press, 1992). Appears courtesy of the author.</metadata>
</root>
